okay well let's see if we can do a a
one-take
stream of consciousness um expression of
a at least my version of the the theory
of the adjacent possible
so this is a reference to stuart
kaufman's theory of the adjacent
possible
and has been significantly influenced by
conversations with
greg heinrichs and his theory of the
talk the theory of knowledge
all right so here's the notion let's say
you've got a
a garage and in the garage you've got a
bunch of piece parts
legos you have some ability to put legos
together
and the the notion is that on occasion
when you put legos together there's like
a
a click and some new piece part emerges
i'm trying to make this simple so let's
say you've got 100 legos
well the number of possible combinations
right i can have
every pairwise connection that i can
also have every triatic connection every
four connection all the way up to every
99 connection which is a very large
space
this is stewart's theory a very large
space of possible combinations
and i essentially have three
inquiries all right and that now i'm
going to start going further into the
into i don't know whether or not what
i'm saying is is straight
mainstream stewart's theory or or just
my own sort of weird variation on it so
just bear with me
all right so i've got my my box of 100
pieces
and i i start putting them together and
then i get a click
all right something new has happened now
here's the key now i have 101 pieces
all right so the space of combinatorics
went from a hundred
things that i could potentially put
together in all these different
configurations to 101
right now of course that increases the
whole space geometrically
and the next click i now have 102 and
the whole space continues to go up
geometrically
all right now here's the thing
i'm going to identify the the sort of
the combinatorial of all possible
combinations
as the possibility space possibility
space
one and then and then when i move to a
new so if we move from 100 to 101
i've gone out to a possibility space two
101 so there's a
and there's some sort of uh volume i'm
just going to use volume to represent
the notion of
geometry so as the as the number of
things to be combined increases the
number of
possible things increases at a at a rate
that is
is has a geometric relationship with
that
some kind of exponent okay now
here's the trick as i'm um
increasing the the space as i'm
increasing the volume
that could be explored the possibility
space is increasing
but i still actually have two
fundamental constraints um
the first constraint is something like
the
the number of combinations i can
actually test
given uh finite time
and energy and so so each time that i go
you know
test that takes time and it takes some
amount of energy
and assuming i have both finite time and
energy
there's actually a a finite number of of
tests that i can undergo all right so
if i imagine that as a a sphere
of a different color superimposed in my
previous sphere so let's say my first
sphere is
uh um white my second sphere is red
then um let's say for the be in the
beginning i go into this garage i have
objects and i can test um
you know one combination per second and
i'm not going to do the math right now
it's a stream of consciousness right off
right off the cuff that describes a
sphere of number of tests that i can
actually do let's say for the moment
that that's
bigger than the number of tests so i've
got three pieces i can definitely take
all three you know one one with two one
with three
two is three and then one two and three
together done did it work yes or no
okay so the sphere of red the sphere of
number of tests that i can
do and the sphere of white the number of
tests that could be done there's a
relationship between the two now
as i get a yes the number of of
tests that could be done right the white
sphere increases
now here's the question there's a point
at which
when the white sphere is bigger than the
red sphere
the rate limiter on my capacity to be in
relationship with
generatively with the adjacent possible
is actually the red sphere not the white
sphere
and so as i continue to explore and find
clicks i'm increasing that white sphere
but if my red sphere is not
also increasing i start actually finding
myself limited by this
search through an increasingly large
space right and at some point
there's like a moment of of overwhelm
for those of you who happen to be human
beings on the internet
right now you may be familiar with this
notion right the possibility space
of relationships that we can currently
engage in is
not just vast it's sort of hyper vast
and hyper vastly larger
than our current capacity to discern
which relationships to actually engage
in right so there's a
sort of a possibility space there's a
mechanism
to select the which of those
possibilities to
actually invest time and energy into and
then the third move
is there's a degree to which the actual
consequences of those relationships has
a
a generative impact and what i mean by
generative impact here
is remember my my my block so i have a
a hundred blocks let's say i can i can
only test say
uh ten thousand combinations right so
which of
all the possible combinations do i
actually test that's the second move
and what's the process by which i make
that choice right that's you know it
could be random
but brandon's not going to work very
well for very long then i've got the
okay what actually happens if i start
putting them together
do i get any clicks did i increase my
possibility space at all
and to what degree this is the
super nuance to what degree did my
particular click
increase my red sphere
in addition to or symmetric width or
maybe even more than
the white sphere all right so let's
let's look at this in the in a more
concrete
that's the abstraction right i've got
those three moves i've got the
the the actual size the possibility
space i've got the mechanism by which i
select the finite number of actual
experiments or combinatorial
possibilities that i can run
and then i've got the actual generative
consequences in relationship to
a does it increase the size of the
possibility space and
b that is does it increase the size of
my
the red sphere my capacity to select
okay now
if you look at this in the context of
say complex chemistry which is actually
where
stuart began the process
um i have a bit of what's called a
portal pathway portal pathways i think
are going to turn out to be super
important here
um so complex chemistry space is the
the sort of the set of combinatorials
the combinations
between um uh molecules
right so in the beginning i've got
certain kinds of molecules that can or
can't connect
and then i get a i get a click and i get
hydrogen and oxygen
connect and now i've got water and water
is a different kind of thing than just
hydrogen and oxygen so the the
possibility of space just increased a
lot i can have a whole bunch of other
kinds of
combinations and of course i can have
water now combining with
other kinds of molecules so i got this
huge milieu
of of the combinatorics that can happen
inside complex chemistry space
um okay now now i want you to think
about a particular location
in complex chemistry space which has to
do with
this these three three kinds of complex
chemistry
one is known as dna one is known as
rna and one is known as a uh
a cell a cellular membrane a lipid
membrane that has all of these have
characteristics within each other now
let's say for the moment that i happen
to have by sure chemistry
locked upon a particular configuration
where i have
a bunch of amino acids nucleotides
coordinated into a relationship of a
double helix dna
strand of rna
and coordinated into a complex of a cell
membrane
by sheer complex chemistry right
now what's the likelihood what's the
probability
that in the next that there's a there's
going to be a uh
in the next moment or in any future
moment i will arrive at
an absolutely identical copy of that
same
chemistry in in complex chemistry space
the probability of
verges on zero just stochastic
combinations i may get dna and rna and
cell membrane again
but the likelihood i'll get the exact
same one effectively zero
but then we have this other thing this
other tool
so the red sphere this other way of
searching the the combinatorials
available in complex chemistry space
which is known as
cellular replication right mitosis dna
synthesis
where um this very specific
characteristics that were unlocked in
the innovation in the discovery of dna
rna and cell membranes
give rise to the ability to copy that
exact set of complex chemistry
into a new cell with a probability
near one right so my body is made up of
trillions and trillions of cells
they successfully copy each other in
fact copy each other with complex
branchings of exactly how they
differentiate
almost perfectly almost all the time
right so
compare that to what would happen in
just a stochastic random chemistry
and of course this insight the whole
this insight of the the unbelievable
collapse of the the probability
landscape into a very very
narrow bound of what actually happens is
the thing that stewart was
was was working on so that's the the
inside of the space
so we have that example now okay let's
take a look now i'm going to branch into
greg's work talk so the same kind of
threshold and i'm going to
use the concept of a portal pathway
which i'm not sure if i've described it
before but it's a cool concept
i have the the set of possibilities in
complex chemistry space
then i kind of unlock this super cool
combination
that has a a radical shift
in the uh the red sphere which is to say
a radical shift in the
the set of of experimental or the exp
the set of combinations that are
actualized that gives rise to
uh what it turns out to be a whole new
landscape a whole new milieu right so
now we're in
life space and life space is different
than complex chemistry space live space
is
governed by this new probability
landscape
um that the of dna rna and cell
membranes
that radically changes the prob the
exactly what
piece of the total space of complex
chemistry
is in fact where you're searching right
you're only searching
inside that space looking for very
specific combinations
of complex chemistry that are
fully compatible 100 compatible with
um with with dna rna
cell right and now of course but there's
lots of variations in there that's a
whole new adjacent possible but now
we've unlocked this thing
and we actually it's interesting we stay
within a very very narrow
space in complex chemistry but now we've
discovered there's a very
large adjacent possible
inside that narrow space and that
actually it opens up right the whole
story of
biological evolution is the exploration
of what's inside that space what's
inside that territory
and by the way this iterates inside
biology space it turns out there's
neurology space and we can go into
really cool detail about exactly what is
the threshold where
the emergence of the ability to
constrain
the coordination of a diverse number of
perception and actuation agents i.e
cells in a multicellular organism
to a dispositional orientation move
right so
photosensitive cells have this ability
to shift the input output
uh i guess algorithms of just
effectively against stochastic behavior
what what do the cells do
into a coordinated behavior known as
behavior right so neurology
gives rise to the beginning of an
entirely new milieu and evolution space
which is behavior space this is all uh
greg's stuff greg does a great job here
so
greg i'll put a link in the video all
right so
adjacent possible white sphere red
sphere
the actual trajectory do you actually
hit something where you've unlocked a
new a new
move this notion of portal pathways that
there's moments where you can actually
unlock an entirely new milieu
which is very narrowly within the legacy
space it's a very specific subset of
legacy
space but actually by virtue of holding
that particular location
so radically changes the probability
landscape in the old space that you've
actually opened up a whole new space
um which is super ordinate to it
by the way behavior space neurology
space
now uh there's a particular location in
that
known as culture space a symbolic
mediated coordination of biologically
discrete
social animals right so you've got this
capacity in neurology space to begin
engaging in signaling
that is outside the body and you can
start coordinating social groups you
start having social animals
in the context of social animals there's
a very specific zone where a certain
level of perception
and signaling capacity and bandwidth and
all these other characteristics
gives rise to this new thing called
culture right now
in the context of culture space there's
a very specific narrow band
that if you hit it just right radically
increases the
or radically changes the probability
landscape and gives rise to a portal
pathway
to a whole new thing that by the way is
known as game b